Okay, בוקר
טוב, Boker Tov, good morning everyone. גוט חודש. Gut Chodesh.
We begin today with on נ"ד עמוד ב'. Nun Daled Amud Bet.
I don't know what דף Daf we would say today's דף Daf
is, but anyway. We begin on נ"ד עמוד ב', Nun Daled Amud
Bet, and we are five lines down in the גמרא. Gemara. And
we had a list in the משנה Mishnah of things a נזיר
Nazir is not מגלח. Megale'ach. Some because they are only רבנן, Rabanan,
and some even though they're דאורייתא, D'oraisa, like טומאת מת, Tumas Meis,
they are excluded from the category of נזיר Nazir מגלח. Megale'ach. And
in parallel, as I've mentioned to you, not mentioned in the גמרא,
Gemara, but in מסכת שמחות, Masechet Smachot, it says that anything a
נזיר Nazir is not מגלח, Megale'ach, doesn't have to shave his head
and doesn't destroy the earlier days, bring a קרבן Korban and so
on, is not included in the prohibitions for a כהן. Kohen. So
that is very significant and we'll get to that. But right now
we're dealing with the more, you know, obvious category of exclusion, the
things that are only רבנן. Rabanan. So the first thing we started
with are things that it's not that we're dealing with a real
מת, Meis, but the means of conveying the טומאה Tumah is רבנן.
Rabanan. So that is overhanging trees and outcropping, and outcropping walls. The
case of the trees, the way תוספות Tosafot explains there definitely is
a dead body buried underneath it, maybe the trees in a cemetery.
But the actual branches, the width of the branches and of the
leaves, do not make a דאורייתא אהל D'oraisa Ohel because they're not
a טפח Tefach by טפח Tefach in any one place. The case
of the outcropping walls, if you imagine a big stone outcropping from
a tall wall, obviously that's big and that is an אהל. Ohel.
So that the case is explained, that's the way תוספות Tosafot explains
it is, it's on the what's buried on the outside of the
wall of the cemetery, sometimes people would bury fetuses there, but it's
uncertain, it's a ספק, Safek, so it's a ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים.
Safek Tumah B'reshut Harabbim. And therefore that's why it's only רבנן, Rabanan,
by biblically it is, the person would be טהור. Tahor. So that's
why it's only רבנן Rabanan and the נזיר Nazir is not מגלח.
Megale'ach. So now we pick up with a new category which is
the בית הפרס Beis Hapras and the ארץ העמים. Eretz Ha'amim. So
interestingly in this גמרא, Gemara, בית הפרס Beis Hapras gets a lot
of treatment in a lot of גמרות. Gemaras. It's a field in
which a grave was plowed, you know, accidentally plowed through, and there's
concerns about bits of bone throughout the entire field. So biblically, it
would be a case where there would not be enough of a
basis for concern, it's only if you touch the bone anyway and
so on.
But רבנןly Rabanan you can't walk in the whole field and if
you do you're considered to be טמא. Tamei. That's בית הפרס, Beis
Hapras, we're not going to focus on that. We're going to focus
on ארץ העמים, Eretz Ha'amim, the land outside of Israel is all
considered to be טמא. Tamei. And let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara raises a question about what is
the parameters of that טומאה, Tumah, what aspects of it is טמא,
Tamei, but maybe to some degree that also connects to the reason
why we were מטמא Mitamei it. So let's take a look. So
it says like this: וארץ העמים, V'eretz Ha'amim, it is five lines
down from the top of the דף Daf by the two, by
the two dots. ארץ העמים איבעיא להו. Eretz Ha'amim, Ibaya Lehu. They
raise the question: ארץ העמים משום אוירה גזרו עליה? Eretz Ha'amim Mishum
Avira Gazru Aleha? Did they say the air was a problem? או
דילמא משום גושה גזרו עליה? O Dilma Mishum Gusha Gazru Aleha? Or
was it the dirt that was a problem? Now, what this means
is that clearly if they assume the dirt has let's say dead
bodies, and let's assume even non-Jewish bodies, Jewish bodies, or we'll assume
that we're concerned about טומאת אהל, Tumas Ohel, then it would also
be a problem to be, you know, in the air because you're
over the dirt like flying over a cemetery. So that's included in
גושה. Gusha. גושה Gusha means the dirt and being מהיל Mahil over
the dirt, touching the dirt or just being suspended over the dirt.
Although תוספות Tosafot does say that another גמרא Gemara might question that,
might say that even גושה Gusha is only touching the dirt and
not being מהיל, Mahil, here we'll assume that both are included in
גושה. Gusha. אוירה Avira means even in a case where you would
not be, where you would be protected if there were a dead
body buried in the ground. Like let's say, you know, you were
sitting on top of a platform, you're on the second story in
a house. So anything buried in the ground, the floor below you
would be an אהל Ohel for it, right? So you would be
protected because of the laws of אהל Ohel even if there were
dead bodies buried in the ground. Nevertheless, if you say משום אוירה,
Mishum Avira, it means that the very air is considered to be
טמא. Tamei. You could be totally protected from anything in the ground,
you're on top of an אהל, Ohel, and nevertheless משום אוירה Mishum
Avira means you're טמא Tamei because you're just in the airspace of
ארץ העמים. Eretz Ha'amim. Now there's no logic for this, right? I
mean there are no dead bodies floating around in the air, you
know, that could be a problem. So what is the issue? So
this certainly points to the idea that one of the issues behind
טומאת ארץ העמים Tumas Eretz Ha'amim is not a practical concern of
טומאה. Tumah. So let's take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, and תוספות
Tosafot says the
following: ארץ העמים על אוירה
גזרו,
Eretz Ha'amim Al
Avira Gazru, says תוספות. Tosafot. כגון מהלך בשידה תיבה ומגדל. K'gon Mahlach
B'shida Teva U'migdal. We're about to see this example in the גמרא
Gemara but we might as well read it now in תוספות. Tosafot.
You are being transported in a huge box. It's bigger than forty,
the size of a מקווה. mikveh. Why? Because if it's not bigger
than forty סאה se'ah it's a כלי, kli, and if it's a
כלי kli it wouldn't necessarily serve as an אוהל, ohel, right? A
classic אוהל ohel is a structure, whereas if something is a vessel,
right, so that even if it has a טפח tefach by a
טפח tefach underneath, that might not provide, divide between the two טומאות,
tumos, especially because then it's a vessel, could be מקבל טומאה mekabel
tumah and all those other reasons. Okay, but it's not a כלי.
kli. It's huge. It's like the box that your refrigerator came in,
okay? So it's a huge box and you're in it, and it's
big enough that it's considered not to be a כלי kli and
you are there and you're let's say, I don't know, on a
platform in that box in ארץ העמים Eretz Haamim and the top
is open. So anything underneath you, it's an אוהל, ohel, the bottom
of the box is an אוהל, ohel, it's מפסיק. mafsik. All right?
Okay, או נכנס בקרונות או בספינה O nichnas bikronot o bispina or
you entered into the ארץ העמים Eretz Haamim in a boat or
you're in a wagon, okay? And again, the anything underneath you between
you and the ground is a אוהל ohel and you're protected. שהחמירו
בו, She'hechmiru vo, now, how would it be that you would be
טמא tamei if you're just in the air space? If you're on
top of an אוהל ohel that's between you and the ground, how
could you be טמא? tamei? So here's the idea: שהחמירו בו יותר
מבאוהל המת. She'hechmiru vo yoter mib'ohel hamet. They were more strict by
the air space of ארץ העמים Eretz Haamim more than really issues
about dead bodies and אוהל ohel and all those things, even though
you're on top of an אוהל. ohel. Now, כדי, K'dei, and here
the key words in תוספות: Tosfos: שלא יצא מארץ לחוץ לארץ. Shelo
yeitzei me'eretz l'chutz la'aretz.
So it's a completely type of a, you know, using הלכה halacha
as a means
of policy or, you know, societal legislation,
so in order to address a societal issue or a well-being of
the, you know, of the Jewish nation or of the land of
Israel, we're going to say the land outside of Israel's טמאה, tmeia,
and that will prevent people from going outside of Israel. So only
prevent כהנים kohanim from going outside of Israel, which is interesting, like,
you know, maybe sort of it'll lead to a more religious attitude.
Ugh, who wants to be in חוץ לארץ? chutz la'aretz? It's all
טמא. tamei. Okay, but the actual, you know, and there's also other
things that prevent people from going to חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, like
the הלכה halacha that it's אסור לצאת מארץ ישראל לחוץ לארץ. assur
latzeit me'eretz Yisrael l'chutz la'aretz.
Okay, so,
isn't that sufficient enough?
Well, maybe not. You know, כהנים kohanim were much more responsive to
laws of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah than to... well, they did say
אסור לצאת מארץ ישראל לחוץ לארץ assur latzeit me'eretz Yisrael l'chutz la'aretz
for everybody. I know. So I'm saying the immediate implication of טומאה
tumah is for כהנים, kohanim, but it maybe also bleeds into a
certain attitude about, ugh, חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz is all ארץ טמאה,
eretz tmeia, you know? So it's very interesting that this is not
based on a real concern, certainly not that would have explained the
air space, that's, and maybe the whole thing, maybe all the טומאה,
tumah, meaning you could say, well the additional חומרא chumrah of the
air space is this, but it doesn't sound like that. It sounds
like the whole thing is emerging from a way of getting people
not to leave, you know, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for חוץ לארץ.
chutz la'aretz. Or maybe the opposite, get כהנים, kohanim, get people to
come from חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael if
you develop this whole thing about חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz is טמא.
tamei. So,
so that's really interesting from the perspective of משום אווירא גזרו. mishum
avira gazru. And then one wonders even if you say משום גושא
גזרו, mishum gusha gazru, maybe that's even what's behind משום גושא גזרו,
mishum gusha gazru, it just doesn't go as overboard, right? But the
problem about גושא gusha is that it's one thing if you touch
the dirt, you could say you're concerned that there are dead bodies,
but if it's non-Jews, then even if there are dead bodies buried
all over, you'd have to come in contact with it. So what
would be the concern about just walking? I mean what? Are we
concerned about little bits of bones of non-Jews everywhere? I mean, what
are we concerned about? So even גושא gusha there's not really a
good argument. So if you look at the next line of תוספות
Tosfos he says, או דילמא משום גושא גופא, O dilma mishum gusha
gufa, המהלך על גושא גזרו, hamahalech al gusha gazru, so vis-a-vis the
dirt and only laws of אוהל. ohel. Now how does אוהל ohel
matter if it's חוץ לארץ? chutz la'aretz? So he says,
כמו המהלך על מת מפני מתי מבול k'mo hamahalech al met mipnei
metei mabul או מפני רוב ישראל שנהרגו בחוץ לארץ. o mipnei rov
Yisrael shenehergu b'chutz la'aretz. So where are, if it's about מהלך, mahalech,
you're not, right, and where it has to be Jews if that's
how we פוסקין, poskin, I mean you could say maybe this doesn't
פסק pasken that, but assuming we פוסקין poskin that only Jews are
מטמא באוהל, metamei b'ohel, so where are all the dead Jews in
חוץ לארץ? chutz la'aretz? And תוספות Tosfos says first of all, well,
very appropriate this week's פרשה, parsha, okay, and if שנער Shinar or
חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz was בבל, Bavel, and they believe, you know,
there's an idea that בבל Bavel because it was very low is
where all there's other גמרות gemaras it says all of the... right,
שנער Shinar whatever, all of the dead bodies of the מבול mabul
were washed into, you know, were washed into בבל Bavel and they're
buried under the ground of בבל. Bavel. Okay, that's interesting, but there's
only a problem: they weren't Jewish. So I don't understand. First of
all, בבל Bavel isn't all of חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, and second
of all, I don't exactly get how that solves the Jewish problem,
right? Maybe that first answer of תוספות Tosfos assumes that we're פוסקין
poskin even non-Jews are מטמא באוהל, metamei b'ohel, and then he says
רוב ישראל שנהרגו בחוץ לארץ. rov Yisrael shenehergu b'chutz la'aretz. I mean,
again, that's pretty tragic. I mean obviously, you know, after the Holocaust
certainly, you know, whatever, we
can... time of חז"ל, Chazal, I mean even in the time when
they were destroying the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, most of the deaths
occurred in Israel, didn't occur outside of Israel. So even משום גוש
mishum gush that follows normal laws of טומאה tumah and טהרה, taharah,
it doesn't really logically work if you need it to be אוהל
ohel over the body of Jews. So it could be that all
the legislation is fundamentally coming from this idea of כדי שלא יצאו
מארץ ישראל לחוץ לארץ kedei shelo yeitzu mei'Eretz Yisrael l'Chutz La'aretz and
then it's a question, that's what motivates it, but do we then
sort of apply normal laws of טומאה tumah and טהרה taharah and
treat it like טומאת אוהל tumas ohel all around, or do we
go even further and say the very air space is מטמא metamei
even if you're protected by an אוהל? ohel? How far do we
go? Okay, so it's very interesting what this might reflect in terms
of what's behind this aspect of חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. David, you
had a question.
I was just about airplane, does that act as an אוהל? ohel?
So we're going to get to that. Basic answer is no for
two reasons. Number one is that it's מטלטל, metaltel, so it's not
חוצץ בפני הטומאה, chotzetz bifnei hatumah, and the other reason is that
it's an אוהל זרוק ohel zaruk which we're going to get to,
that's not stationary, but we're going to get to that actually very
soon. Okay, Charlie, you have.
Yeah, so 2,000 years after this משנה Mishna was written,
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael has been invaded so many times and Jews
have been massacred so many times in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Right.
And you see that today, almost every time someone builds a building,
they
find— Right.
Old graves and go nuts.
Right. That the whole country is a cemetery. Right. This would seem
to be a big issue for ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
I know, I know. Yeah, it's an excellent point. The irony goes
even further, you're absolutely correct. Yeah, which just goes to show that
it's much more about this כדי שלא יצאו kedei shelo yeitzu reason,
I think whatever form it takes, I think that clearly has to
be the underlying thing of what's going on here.
The underlying— כל טומאה שאין הנזיר מגלח עליה אין כהן מוזהר עליה.
kol tumah she'ein ha'nazir megaleach aleha ein kohen muzhar aleha.
Yeah, כל טומאה שאין הנזיר מגלח עליה אין כהן מוזהר עליה.
kol
tumah
she'ein ha'nazir megaleach aleha ein kohen muzhar aleha. We'll get to that
in a bit, okay? We'll see that in תוספות. Tosafot.
Which is also a worldview that— I don't want to say it's
negative about the world, but—
Well, negative about חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
Well, you know, most of the world.
Right. Well, you know, it's a New Yorker's view of the world.
It's just as—
most of the world is Israel, everything else is like
חוץ לארץ.
Chutz La'aretz. You know, there's more Jews buried in Israel than anywhere
else.
Right, right, it is, and
it
isn't a problem for a כהן kohen because it doesn't— מגלח megaleach
in ארץ העמים. Eretz Amim.
Well, he's not מוזהר עליו, muzhar alav, he doesn't get lashes on—
like a כהן kohen can't go to a בית הפרס, beis haperas,
I mean that's worth pointing out. When I referenced that and that
isn't in the גמרא, Gemara, but it's going to be very relevant
when we get to the שכונת הפרס sh'chunas hapras discussion. But that
idea that a כהן kohen is not מוזהר עליו, muzhar alav, okay,
doesn't mean that it's מותר. muttar. There's still איסורי דרבנן issurei d'rabbanan
for a כהן kohen to go in בית הפרס, beis haperas, שדות
הפרס, shados haperas, ארץ העמים, Eretz Amim, all those things are איסורי
דרבנן issurei d'rabbanan for a כהן. kohen. The question is whether they
get lashes.
Okay, so when we say מוזהר עליו muzhar alav we mean—
Yeah, מלקות דאורייתא, malkus d'Oraisa, איסור דאורייתא. issur d'Oraisa. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's the question. משום אוירא
גזרו עלה, mishum avira gazru alah, is it just the air space
even if you're protected by an אוהל? ohel? או דילמא משום גוש
גזרו עלה, o dilma mishum gush gazru alah, or is it because
of the dirt and therefore if you're protected by an אוהל ohel
you're safe? תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. ומזה בשלישי ובשביעי.
umazei bashlishi uvashvii.
So it says that if somebody went into ארץ העמים, Eretz Amim,
it doesn't just destroy their— they don't have to shave their head,
doesn't destroy their נזירות, nezirus, they don't bring a קרבן, korban, but
they have to become טהור tahor and they have to sprinkle on
days three and seven. ומזה בשלישי ובשביעי. umazei bashlishi uvashvii. ואי אמרת
משום אוירא, v'ei amart mishum avira,
if it's the air, so the גמרא Gemara says if it's the
air then clearly we're not dealing with any form of normal טומאה
tumah and טהרה. taharah. It's not only a דרבנן d'rabbanan extension of
normal טומאה tumah and טהרה, taharah, it's a new invention. The air
space is מטמא. metamei. So if it's a new invention it's not
based on טומאת מת, tumas meis, it's just a new idea, ארץ
העמים Eretz Amim is מטמא metamei on its own, even the air
space. So if that's true, הזאה למה לי? haza'ah lamah li? Why
would you do the sprinkling, right? You're no longer trying to put
it in the framework of טומאת מת. tumas meis. It's one thing
to say, okay, don't have questions why I'm assuming that there're dead
Jews buried all over in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, but that's what
we're assuming and then it works like טומאת מת tumas meis and
then דרבננית d'rabbananis I can require you to do sprinkling on שלישי
ושביעי. shlishi v'shvii. But if I say the air space, I'm obviously
creating a very new type of a טומאה. tumah. So how if
I'm creating this new טומאה tumah that the very air space is
מטמא, metamei, can I tell you that it's based on טומאת מת
tumas meis and that you should be sprinkling on שלישי ושביעי? shlishi
v'shvii? There's no basis. It's obviously a new טומאה, tumah, so why
would I sprinkle? So הזאה למה לי? haza'ah lamah li? אלא לאו
משום גוש, ela lav mishum gush, you see it's based on the
dirt and it's working within the framework of טומאת מת. tumas meis.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no. לעולם אימא לך, le'olam
eima lach, I'll tell you משום אוירא, mishum avira, it is the
air space. והכי קתני אחזאה, v'hachi kasni achaza'ah, your assumption is right,
if it's the air space it's not a טומאת מת tumas meis
concept. It's a new טומאה, tuma, there would not be sprinkling on
שלישי ושביעי. shlishi veshvi'i. When did it say sprinkle on שלישי ושביעי?
shlishi veshvi'i? On the other things in the list. There are other
things that mention סככות sechachos and פרעות, peraos, it mentions בית הפרס.
beis hapras. Those are things which are based on טומאת מת, tumas
meis, those are שלישי ושביעי. shlishi veshvi'i. There are other things in
this list which it wouldn't be relevant for, so ארץ העמים eretz
ha'amim would not have that, it's a completely different type of a
טומאה. tuma. Okay, now, you by the way you know that's clear
because the end of the list also talks about a מצורע. metzora.
Right? It says or if he's a מצורע, metzora, it doesn't contradict,
but you can't start counting until he becomes טהור, tahor, whatever, and
it also says at the end of all the list שלישי ושביעי.
shlishi veshvi'i. Well, obviously that's not relevant for מצורע, metzora, the sprinkling
of the ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So what the
גמרא Gemara is saying is, so this idea that you sprinkle on
שלישי ושביעי shlishi veshvi'i for the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, of the
פרה אדומה, parah adumah, that's on some of the things of the
list. It's obviously not on the מצורע, metzora, it is on the
סככות sechachos and the פרעות peraos and the בית הפרס. beis hapras.
So if ארץ העמים eretz ha'amim is a different type of a
טומאה, tuma, that it would not apply to that either.
What about גולל ודופק? golel and dofek? גולל ודופק golel and dofek
it would apply to, thank you, I forgot that.
Because it's sort of weird that ארץ העמים eretz ha'amim is in
the middle, because the list is
סככות, sechachos, פרעות, peraos, בית הפרס.
beis hapras. Yes, ארץ העמים eretz ha'amim no, and גולל ודופק golel
and dofek yes?
Yes, I know. It's a very good point. Okay, but it applies
to the things on the list which it's relevant for. I understand,
it's a strong question. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara says you're right,
if ארץ העמים eretz ha'amim is the air space, then it's the
very air, then it's a different טומאה, tuma, you would not have
שלישי ושביעי, shlishi veshvi'i, and that line in the משנה Mishnah doesn't
apply to everything in the משנה. Mishnah. Now, the גמרא Gemara says,
הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistabra, now here it becomes a very
important line, and we're going to digress a little bit with this
תוספות Tosafos to discuss this next line, there on this next line,
to digress a little bit from the ארץ העמים. eretz ha'amim. הכי
נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistabra, that also makes sense that the idea
of שלישי ושביעי shlishi veshvi'i does not apply to everything on the
list, מדקתני mideka tanni וכלים הנוגעים במת. vekeilim hanog'im bemeis. Another thing
on the list is if the נזיר nazir touched vessels that touched
a dead body. הני כלים בני הזאה נינהו? hani keilim benei haza'ah
nin? Would you sprinkle with שלישי ושביעי shlishi veshvi'i for somebody who
came in contact with vessels? So אלא שמע מינה אשארא, ela shema
mina ash'arei, it must be that it's not talking about everything on
the list, only on some things of the list. Now, why does
the גמרא Gemara take it for granted that you would not sprinkle
for somebody who came in contact with vessels? Well, let's think about
it. If you just had the normal הלכה halakha of vessels, if
you hadn't been primed with this idea of חרב הרי הוא כחלל,
cherev harei hu kechalal, you would say a vessel that touches a
מת meis is an אב הטומאה. av hatuma. A person who touches
an אב הטומאה av hatuma is a ראשון. rishon. A ראשון rishon
only is טמא tamei for one day, right? So there's no sprinkling
of שלישי ושביעי, shlishi veshvi'i, the נזיר nazir is not מגלח, megale'ach,
everything makes sense. Okay, so that might be what the גמרא Gemara
is assuming, okay, that we're just talking about you know normal vessels.
And that's why. But of course then it's bizarre, why is it
even bothered to be mentioned in a משנה Mishnah if it's just
a normal type of a one day טומאה? tuma? What's going on
there? So take a look here at תוספות Tosafos and this is
going to get us into the question about חרב הרי הוא כחלל.
cherev harei hu kechalal. Okay? So תוספות Tosafos says like this, 1,
2, 3, 4 lines down: תא שמע. tashma. Four lines down, middle
of the line, four lines down in the wide lines where it
says ואם תאמר, ve'im tomar, really smack in the middle of the
line. You see that? Okay, ואם תאמר: ve'im tomar: ולישני ליה דהני
כלים בכלי מתכות מיירי דאדם הנוגע בהם טמא טומאת
שבעה ובעי הזאת ג' וז' דחרב כחלל. uleishnei lei dehani keilim bichlei
machas mairi, de'adam hanogea bahem tamei tumas shiv'ah, uba'ei haza'as gimmel vezayin,
decherev kechalal. Why I don't understand, why does it take for granted
that these כלים keilim don't create a seven day טומאה? tuma? Why
doesn't it say that these are metal כלים, keilim, it's based on
this principle we learned the other day of חרב כחלל, cherev kechalal,
okay,
and therefore they become like the מת meis itself and somebody who
touches them becomes an אב הטומאה? av hatuma? And then it would
not be an exception to the list, it would be a seven
day טומאה tuma and it would have a sprinkling of שלישי ושביעי.
shlishi veshvi'i. Why is it assuming that it's a trivial case of
כלים? keilim? If it's so trivial, why is it even being mentioned
anyway? Right? Why? So you get the question, right? If we assume
it's normal כלים, keilim, big deal, so the נזיר nazir is a
ראשון לטומאה, rishon letuma, like you don't even have to say that
in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, it's more interesting if we assume it's
the principle of חרב כחלל, cherev kechalal, therefore the כלים keilim are
like the מת, meis, the נזיר nazir is seven days, right, and
then so A that would be a bigger חידוש chiddush and
B it wouldn't be an exception, it would be שלישי ושביעי, shlishi
veshvi'i, you would need a sprinkling of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
So why isn't it assuming that we're talking about חרב כחלל? cherev
kechalal? So let's see תוספות's Tosafos answer.
ואומר רבינו תם: ve'omer Rabbeinu Tam: דעל כרחך לא מוקמה מתניתין בכלי
מתכות. de'al karchach lo mikukma masnisin bichlei machas. It can't be talking
about metal and חרב כחלל, cherev kechalal, and where the guy who
touches it is טמא tamei for seven days. Why not? דאם כן
הנזיר מגלח דחרב הרי הוא כחלל. de'im kein hanazir megale'ach, decherev harei
hu kechalal. Because if that was the case, that would have been
a more interesting and a bigger חידוש. chiddush. But רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam says: but if that's then here the נזיר nazir would be
מגלח, megale'ach, if it really was the principle of חרב הרי הוא
כחלל cherev harei hu kechalal and it was like the מת meis
and the נזיר nazir who touched it would be טמא tamei seven
days, then he would be מגלח. megale'ach. Why should we assume the
נזיר nazir wouldn't be מגלח? megale'ach? Okay meaning like I understand. So
that's רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam is saying: we have a דרשה drasha
that חרב הרי הוא כחלל cherev harei hu kechalal and that we
don't have any גמרא Gemara that tells us that a נזיר nazir
is not מגלח. megale'ach. So thank you. So רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
is saying that I will assume that a נזיר nazir is מגלח.
megale'ach. And that's why we can't be talking about חרב כחלל. cherev
kechalal. You can't assume that that's what's going on in the משנה
mishna *Mishnah*. So you got this next line is a classic. Let's
read the next line. ושלח לו רבנו חיים הכהן *V'shalach lo Rabbeinu
Chaim HaKohen*. So רבנו חיים הכהן *Rabbeinu Chaim HaKohen*, notice, sent the
following letter to רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam *Rabbeinu Tam*. Okay, and he
sent him, איזה בית אשר תבנו לי *Aizeh bayis asher tivnu li*,
anybody recognize that? ואיזה מקום מנוחתי *V'aizeh makom menuchati*, right, where God
says, what type of a house can you make for me, right,
you know? So, so he says, I'm a כהן kohen. *Kohen*, you're
telling me that any metal that was in the house with the
מת meis *meis* is not only treated like the מת meis *meis*,
but actually I am biblically prohibited to come in contact with it,
right? That's what you're saying, חרב כחלל cherev k'chalal, *cherev k'chalal* will
treat it literally, and I'm biblically prohibited to be in the same
house where this is present. How can you ever what house can
you build for me? How can I ever be in any house?
Why not? Because listen to what he says: דאין נזיר nazir מגלח
m'gale'ach עליו *de-ein Nazir megalei'ach alav*, what house can you build for
me that won't be a case of נזיר nazir מגלח m'gale'ach *Nazir
megalei'ach*? הוא הדין דכל דבר שיהיה וגו' דאין נזיר nazir מגלח m'gale'ach,
עליו הוא הדין דכל דבר *Hu hadin de-chol davar she-yehei v'chu de-ein
Nazir megalei'ach alav hu hadin de-chol davar* or excuse me, דדבר שדאין
*de-davar she-de-ein*. If a נזיר nazir *Nazir* is מגלח m'gale'ach. *megalei'ach* עליו
*alav*, הוא הדין דכהן מוזהר muzhar. עליו *hu hadin de-kohen muzhar alav*.
ואין לך בית שאין בו שום כלי מתכות kli matachos, שהיה באהל
המת או שום מסמר כדאמרינן במסכת מכות כל טומאה tumah. שהנזיר מגלח
m'gale'ach עליה כהן kohen מוזהר עליה *V'ein lecha bayis she-ein bo shum
k'lei matechos she-hayah b'ohel hameis o shum masmer k'd'amrinan b'Maseches Makkos kol
tumah she-ha-Nazir megalei'ach aleha kohen muzhar aleha*. So here we have that
key line that if it's the link between what is a נזיר
nazir *Nazir* מגלח m'gale'ach *megalei'ach* is what is the כהן kohen *Kohen*
is prohibited. And he says any house, now this is interesting, he
says any house that has nails, those nails once were in a
house that had a מת meis *meis*. Now really? Like, I don't
know, I got fresh new brand new nails from Home Depot, okay,
but of course presumably that's not what they did in the middle
ages, right? I presume, you know, it was a lot harder to
make nails or whatever. You take down one house, you preserve the
nails for the next house, okay? Or sometime, I don't know, you
know, things you buy stuff in the in the market and you
buy some metal vessel which who knows, one time in its history
it was in it was in a house that there was a
dead body. What had to go through my life avoiding, like, you
know, metal vessels my whole life because maybe it was in a
place where there was a dead body? So he says like it's
impossible that we would apply חרב כחלל cherev k'chalal *cherev k'chalal* to
the point that we would say that נזיר nazir *Nazir*'s מגלח megaleiach?
*megalei'ach* and that a כהן kohen *Kohen* is מוזהר *muzhar*. And therefore,
he says, it must be when the משנה mishna *Mishnah* says כלים
keilim, הנוגעים במת *keilim ha-nogim b'meit* is that you are that a
נזיר nazir *Nazir* is not מגלח megaleiach *megalei'ach*, that must be talking
even about metal vessels. And even חרב כחלל cherev k'chalal *cherev k'chalal*,
a נזיר nazir *Nazir* is not מגלח megaleiach. *megalei'ach*. Okay? And this
is what רב חיים כהן *Rav Chaim Kohen* says, and bottom line
is that that's pretty much the way that the הלכה halacha *halacha*
gets accepted. I want to tell you that the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam*
takes an even more extreme position. And the רמב"ם Rambam, *Rambam* says,
well in two ways. The רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* on the one hand
says, because no גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ever said what are the parameters
of חרב כחלל cherev k'chalal *cherev k'chalal*. It just says חרב כחלל
cherev k'chalal. *cherev k'chalal*. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* assumes it means metal
vessels. רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* actually says that it means all vessels are
טמא tamei *tamei* like the מת met, *meis* itself. All vessels that
were in the same house even non-metal. Now it's actually an interesting
רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* because he actually has a nice on the one
hand he has a nice דרשה drasha. *drasha* of where we get
this idea of חרב כחלל cherev kechalal *cherev k'chalal*. Let me read
you the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* here. Hold on, what's my phone doing?
Hold on a second, my phone's being weird on me.
Can everything just applies to something that killed somebody? What? Just something
that killed somebody?
Right, but from the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* it's clear that the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* applies it to כלים keilim הנוגעים במת *keilim ha-nogim b'meit*.
But the question is like our phrase, but the question is like
what exactly are the parameters of that. Hold on, my phone, okay,
I'll pull it up. On the one hand but I'll find I'll
show you the רמב"ם Rambam, *Rambam* has a nice דרשה *drasha* of
חרב כחלל cherev kechalal, *cherev k'chalal* as well of where he gets
it from. But
what the רמב"ם Rambam? *Rambam* says is besides the דרשה *drasha* which
I'll wait till the okay, here we go. So the רמב"ם Rambam,
*Rambam* says like this, he says, this is in
הלכות טומאת מת met. ה
ג *Hilchos Tumas Meis Hey Gimmel*.
כלים keilim שנטמאו במת בין
במגע בין באהל הרי הנוגע בהן כנוגע במת עצמו *Keilim she-nitme'u b'meis
bein b'maga bein b'ohel harei ha-nogei'a ba-hen k'nogei'a b'meis atzmo*. מה מת
met. מטמא metamei, נוגע בו בין אדם בין כלים keilim. טומאת שבעה
tumat shiva אף כלים keilim. שנטמאו במת הן והכלים או אדם שנגע
בהן טמא טומאת שבעה tamei tumas shivah, *Mah meis metamei nogei'a bo
bein adam bein keilim tumas shivah af keilim she-nitme'u b'meis hein v'hakeilim
o adam she-naga ba-hen tamei tumas shivah*. Now how do we know
this idea? Notice it says כלים keilim *keilim*, not metal, all vessels.
שנאמר בחלל חרב cherev או במת *She-ne'emar be-chalal cherev o b'meis*. מפי
השמועה למדו שהחרב כמת *Mi-pi ha-shmuah lamdu she-cherev k'meis*. והוא הדין לשאר
כלים keilim. *V'hu hadin l'sha'ar keilim*, not just metal vessels, all vessels,
okay? בין כלי kli מתכת בין כלי שטף ובגדים *Bein k'li mateches
bein k'lei shetef uv'gadim*. He recognizes that some people want to limit
it to metal and רמב"ם Rambam, *Rambam* says specifically no, I'm sorry
it's not limited to metal. You should see the נושאי כלים keilim
*nosei keilim* on this רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* go on for pages and
pages and pages. הלכות טומאת מת met ה ג *Hilchos Tumas Meis
Hey Gimmel*, okay, but then he says, now but now he has
a nice דרשה *drasha* that's not in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. הרי
הוא אומר כל הורג נפש וכל נוגע בחלל *Harei hu omer kol
horeg nefesh v'chol nogei'a be-chalal*. Anybody who kills somebody is טמא tamei,
*tamei* for seven days. Now the רמב"ם Rambam, *Rambam* says, really? You
could kill somebody without becoming טמא tamei *tamei*? וכי יעלה על דעתך
שזה ירה חץ והרג או זרק אבן והרג ונטמא שבעת ימים *V'chi
ya'aleh al da'atcha she-zeh yareh cheitz v'harag o zorak even v'harag v'nitma
shivas yamim*? I don't understand what you mean כל הורג נפש *kol
horeg nefesh*? פשוטו נראה *pshuto nira-ah* אלא Ela הורג נפש בחרב *ella
horeg nefesh be-cherev*.
It must mean what would be the scenario that somebody who killed
somebody without coming in contact would be טמא טומאת שבעה tamei tumas
shivah, *tamei tumas shivah*? If he killed him with a sword. Okay?
And therefore that's the that's where we get the idea of חרב
כחלל cherev kechalal *cherev k'chalal* because the... By killing somebody this person
is טמא tamei שבעה, even presumably without touching. So the גמרא Gemara,
says that the scenario would be killing with a sword, so you're
touching the sword. Okay, אלא הרג נפש בחרב וכל יוצא בו שנטמא
בנגיעתו בכלי שהרג בו שהרי נגע הכלי במת. ella horeg nefesh becherev
vechol yotze bo shenitma b'negi'aso b'kli sheharag bo sheharei naga hakli bamet.
Okay,
and then the רמב"ם Rambam, goes on and on. So basically the
first point is first he has a nice דרשה. Second of all,
of course you could have said that maybe it's only when you're
in contact with the כלי with the מת meis at the same
time. But then he generalizes it also to all vessels. At the
same time though, the רמבב"ם Rambam says
that נזיר nazir is not מגלח megaleiach on it. So that's the
leniency for the כהן. Okay, so basically what you wind up having
is three positions. You have
the position that it's only כלי מתכות, only metal. You have רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam that says a נזיר nazir is מגלח on חרב
cherev. כחלל, which means the כהן is אסור. asur. That basically gets
rejected להלכה. l'halacha. Okay, you get the position that it's only metal
and a נזיר nazir is not מגלח, and that's what our משנה
mishna, means when it says כלים שנגעו במת, keilim shenagu bamet, okay,
which is what רבינו חיים Rabbeinu Chaim says. And then you get
the third position of the רמב"ם, Rambam. which is it applies to
all כלים, keilim, but a נזיר nazir is not מגלח. Okay, but
bottom line is is that the consensus winds up being it would
be impossible for כהנים kohanim to go around living their lives if
any vessel or any metal vessel that was with a מת meis
is now they're אסור asur on it like a מת itself. Okay,
so now back to our גמרא. Gemara, Okay, so back to our
גמרא, Gemara, you got a problem, because if the line in the
משנה mishna, of כלים הנגועים במת, keilim hanoguim bamet, if that line
means that what do you call it, that even a חרב cherev
כחלל and even when the guy is טמא tamei? טומאת שבעה, right,
why does the גמרא Gemara. assume
that you're not מזה בשלישי ובשביעי? mazeh b'shlishi u'v'shvii? Right, that's remember
that's where we started? Everybody with me still? Right, it said, look,
saying that in our משנה, mishna the question was if it's only
the airspace of ארץ העמים, eretz ha'amim, why do you have to
sprinkle שלישי ושביעי? shlishi v'shvii? It's obviously a different טומאה. tuma, And
it says, yeah, שלישי ושביעי shlishi v'shvii doesn't apply to everything in
our משנה, mishna like כלים הנגועים במת. keilim hanoguim bamet. Okay, but
if כלים הנגועים במת keilim hanoguim bamet is about חרב כחלל and
it's telling you that a נזיר is not מגלח on that, but
even though you're טמא tamei טומאת שבעה, why is it that you
don't sprinkle בשלישי ובשביעי? b'shlishi u'v'shvii? So that's what תוספות Tosafos tries
to work out, it's not a, that's really a big קשיא, kushya,
and תוספות Tosafot, tries to work it out. רמב"ם Rambam has another
bizarre thing. רמב"ם Rambam says that even though חרב כחלל and you're
טמא tamei for seven days, but there's a special הלכה halacha by
a נזיר that the נזיר not only is not מגלח on it,
but also doesn't have to be מזה שלישי ושביעי mazeh shlishi v'shvii
to become טהור. tahor. So, totally bizarre, totally, totally bizarre. Anyway, it's
a difficult גמרא, Gemara. okay? But bottom line is because of that
line of it, that that's the source where there gets all of
this battleground for what are the parameters of חרב כחלל. Yes.
Do these all the vessels in a house with a dead body?
Or all the metal vessels that were under the same אוהל?
ohel? All the vessels, all the vessels. So what do you do
with those vessels you can't put them in a מקוה mikvah to
purify them? You just...
Well, you could sprinkle on them, you could do the אפר הפרה
אדומה eifer haparah adumah to be מטהר m'taher the vessels if you
wanted to. But according to the רמב"ם Rambam's so it's true, they'd
be you there'd still be a problem.
Clothing,
right?
Right, I mean, look, there'd still be a problem in a world
of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. It could be that if a כהן
isn't אסור, asur, so for nowadays we've solved the problem. But in
a world of טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, you still got the problem
that what do you mean, any vessel that was ever in a
house of a dead body, if anybody ever touches it, they're טמא,
tamei you know, they're טמא tamei, seven days? I mean, think about
just the implications in terms of like eating קדשים kodshim and all
those things. So the answer is you would have to take all
those כלים keilim and go through a process of being מטהר m'taher
them and sprinkle the ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah the whole
thing, the same way you do for the people. I mean, that's
what the תורה Torah says: והזה על האהל ועל כל הכלים ועל
הנפשות אשר היו שם. vehizah al ha'ohel v'al kol hakeilim v'al hanefashos
asher hayu sham. So you go through a process of being מטהר
m'taher everything, yeah.
So assuming that there's a חזקה chazakah that all כלים keilim, have
been in contact with a dead body, all follow the standard rules
of חזקה? chazakah?
Yeah, so I don't know, that's like, I mean, the response of
רבי חיים כהן, Reb Chaim Kohen, I mean it was very poetic,
right, הרי בזה כידיים. horei bazeh k'yadim. The response would be: Okay,
so check it out, go ahead and like the same way we
have to get like a אישור ishur that the אתרוגים esrogim are
not מורכב murkav and are not whatever, go get it, make sure
that you're careful, the houses that are built for the כהנים, kohanim,
you know the provenance of their stuff, or even if you don't,
right, that we shouldn't like make a חזקה chazakah and assume that
everything was that way. Yeah, it is interesting that he says it's
impossible there's not some metal vessel in this house. But your point
could be it's not
impossible. Yeah, but if they really did reuse the nails, and those
were nails that were reused like a dozen times or something, for
hundreds of years, then you could point out people didn't die in
hospitals, people died at home.
Exactly, but the first step is to establish that חזקה. chazakah.
Exactly, but the first step is
to establish that חזקה, chazakah, he leaps over that step.
Right, but the point is that he's using it as a reductio
ad absurdum, so he's not interested in questioning that assumption. But yes,
you could argue back and say, 'I question that assumption and אי
הכי נמי i hachi nami you have to learn how to avoid
it if it's a problem, and you don't have to assume that
it's a problem unless
you know'.
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam is saying it's everything anyway, which is why
then it can't be talking about metal, because then he wouldn't be
having to go through this whole thing. So therefore, he's saying that
the משנה mishna is not talking about metal, right? So it's talking
about...
the משנה mishna isn't talking about metal, and that's why it's not
שלישי ושביעי. shlishi v'shvii. But then the question is...
and the רמב"ם Rambam says something about everything, then that'd be...
and nevertheless, somehow there's a reason that you're not מטמא, metamei. it
doesn't have שלישי ושביעי, shlishi v'shvii, right. But it can still work
that the משנה mishna. is not מטמא. metamei, By the way, if
you want to see that there's a בעל תוספות Baal Tosafot who
I think who agrees with רמב"ם, Rambam if you look with the
line that says
הביא
ראיה מתוספתא דכלים, heivi raya m'tosefta d'keilim, I don't know where to
tell you, it's about literally, it's the line starts with those words.
It's literally like, you know, halfway down the תוספות, Tosafot. sixty percent
down the
תוספות. Tosafot.
One minute, so he says like, oh I'm sorry, no no, I
should have... one minute. Oh no no, wait wait... Oh no, I'm
sorry, I should have gone earlier. ומשמעתין קשיא. u'mishmatin kashya. See what
it says ומשמעתין, u'mishmatin, like five lines above that? The line that
starts with the word ומשמעתין. u'mishmatin. Almost halfway down the תוספות. Tosafot
למה שפירש רב יצחק משמפונט.
lama
shepeireish Rav Yitzchak mi-Simpont.
No, that's
Champagne.
Champagne, Simpont, okay. דמתניתין דאהלות בין בכלי מתכות בין בשאר כלים דכולהו
גמירי מכלי מתכות דאמר חרב הרי הוא כחלל והוא הדין לשאר כלים.
d'matnitin d'Ohalot bein bichli matachot
bein
bishar keilim dikulhu g'mirei michli matachot d'amar cherev harei hu kechalal vehu
hadin lishar keilim. Okay. So that's you see in תוספות Tosafot already
that third opinion that חרב הרי הוא כחלל cherev harei hu kechalal
applies to all vessels. So A, you have the, is it just
metal or is it all vessels? And then the second question is
do we say that a נזיר is מגלח? Okay, and pretty much
everybody says a נזיר is not מגלח except רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam
and then it has very dire consequences. Okay. Yes. You had a
question?
I guess I just don't understand why we're conflating the נזיר and
the just כלים. kelim Like very, it seems to me like as
they were meaning in this משנה mishna to talk
about... Right.
So that's what רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam said... well, if חרב is
the conceptual source, but it's the הלכה halacha expands to כלים. kelim
You don't have to call the כלים kelim. חרב. In the end
of the day, the הלכה halacha is הלכה about כלים. kelim.
Then I just don't understand why use the פסוק pasuk by חרב
and not...
Well, that's just the פסוק pasuk it's learned from. But but the
answer to you is what you're saying is what רבנו תם Rabbeinu
Tam says. רבנו תם says it's just normal כלים kelim and it's
just a normal, you know, טומאת שבעה for the כלים, kelim one
day for the person who touches it. The point is that then
it's not much of a חידוש chiddush to say a נזיר is
not מגלח.
The whole point of that context is that it's trying to prove...
Yes, it works in the גמרא, Gemara but it is not
saying reductio ad absurdum just like having כלים kelim, and saying...
Exactly. So it works in the גמרא, Gemara but it doesn't work
in the משנה. mishna Like why is the משנה mishna mentioning a
normal one-day טומאה, tumah right? But it works in the גמרא. Gemara
So that's exactly the issue. Okay, so let's get back to the
גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistavra, it makes sense that the
משנה mishna, is the idea of שלישי ושביעי shlishi v'shvii doesn't apply
to everything in the משנה mishna מדקתני ובכלים הנוגעים במת. midekatni u'v'keilim
hanogim b'meit. הני כלים מאי נינהו? hani keilim mai ninhu? And just
because you touch those כלים, kelim you wouldn't need to be sprinkled
on שלישי ושביעי. shlishi v'shvii. So that raises all those questions why
not if it's חרב כחלל and so on. But okay, אלא שמע
מינה שרי. ela shma mina sharei. The idea of שלישי ושביעי shlishi
v'shvii doesn't apply to everything in the משנה, so it equally does
not apply
to the idea of אוירא. avira. Okay, so we still have this
open question whether it's אויר avir or גוש. gush. And in the
course of that, we've seen a very important debate of the ראשונים
Rishonim about חרב כחלל, what are its parameters and whether whether that's
what's being referred to in the משנה when it says חרב כחלל
and therefore whether a נזיר is מגלח and whether a כהן is
מוזהר. Now, yes, גמרא Gemara continues. Yes.
I'm sorry, I just can't hold onto this. I don't remember, did
did the תוספות Tosafot know the רמב"ם? Did they have the...
A few תוספותים Tosafotim in ש"ס Shas quote the רמב"ם, like a
handful. So I I don't know, you know, who's the author and
who's the author of this תוספות Tosafot and whatever, right.
It's in other words, this רבנו יצחק Rabbeinu Yitzchak from wherever the
place... Yeah, but the point is,
I said it is the same as the רמב"ם, but you know,
these are, yeah, but but the point is that these are like
the logical range of positions. So the fact that the that you
find a parallel with the position of one of the בעלי תוספות,
Baalei Tosafot, one of the רמב"ם doesn't mean he got it from
the רמב"ם, you know...
No, I was saying the opposite, but that it's the same logical
position. But he doesn't quote the רמב"ם, which is astounding.
No, no, that also
assumes this בעל תוספות Baal Tosafot didn't know that רמב"ם.
No, that raises another question which is, yeah, which is that even
if you're aware of the of of of this of these other
authorities, you doesn't mean that you hold them in the highest esteem
that you, I mean, I don't mean they didn't hold the רמב"ם
in the highest esteem, but it means that no, no, but what
it means is that like, okay, yeah,
there's some ספרדי פוסק Sefardi posek over there that says, I'm sorry,
you know, you know, that says something...
No, I mean the
same, I mean the same thing in the verse!
The same thing in the verse!
Does the רמב"ם ever quote רש"י? Rashi? Oh, not only do I
hold it, רש"י Rashi also says the same thing. Like it was
irrelevant. There was some other ראשון Rishon somewhere else somebody. You have
to think, oh my God, the רמב"ם's a major authority for כל
ישראל. Klal Yisrael. So that's a different
question of
whether... Well, certainly in אשכנז Ashkenaz or whatever. Yeah. All right.
So also there's תוספות Tosafot that died before the רמב"ם was, I
mean like in the 12th century,
the רמב"ם was like not recognized. That's right.
All right. Okay. So let's go on. לימא כתנאי. Lema Katannai. Let's
say this question of אויר או גוש, Avir o Gush, let's say
this question of אויר או גוש Avir o Gush is a debate
of תנאים. Tanna'im. הנכנס לארץ העמים בשידה תיבה ומגדל. Ha-nikhnas le-eretz ha-ammim
be-shidah tevah u-migdal. Somebody goes in—this תוספות Tosafot gave us this scenario—into
the land of חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz in a box, okay,
and or tower or whatever. רבי מטמא ורבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מטהר.
Rabbi metamei ve-Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda metaher. רבי Rabbi says you're טמא
tamei. and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda says you're
טהור. tahor. So this seems to be exactly our case. You're in
this box, so it serves as an אוהל. ohel. So how could
you be טמא? tamei, Must be because of the air. מאי לאו,
Mai lav, רבי סבר משום אוירא, Rabbi savar mishum avira, that it's
the air and therefore it's an open-topped box, okay, and therefore you're
טמא tamei. because you're in the air space. ורבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
סבר משום גושא Ve-Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda savar mishum gusha and he
says, no, it's only the land and the box is serving as
an אוהל. ohel. So that seems to be exactly this debate. No,
not necessarily. דכולי עלמא משום גושא. Dekulei alma mishum gusha. I can
tell you everybody says it's the dirt. So therefore why would you
be טמא tamei. if you're in this box? Isn't the box an
אוהל? ohel? מר סבר אוהל זרוק שמיה אוהל ומר סבר לא שמיה
אוהל. Mar savar ohel zaruk shemei ohel, u-mar savar lo shemei ohel.
The box, the question is that the box is being transported, it's
not stationary. So this is called an אוהל זרוק, ohel zaruk, a
thrown אוהל, ohel, okay, like a frisbee, you know what I mean?
So therefore it's not stationary. Does that have the status of an
אוהל ohel or not? So you're being transported, like they have those,
you know, things with like what they have those rajahs or whatever,
you know, being... palanquin. Okay, that was exactly the word I was
looking for. Okay, you're being transported. How do you know that word?
Okay, so anyway, so is that... everybody holds it's the dirt. Everybody
holds it's the dirt. The question is, does that box that you're
being transported in constitute an אוהל ohel because it is being... it
is moving and it's being transported, like the airplane question. That's the
debate. And it is not a debate of אויר, avir, nobody says
אויר, avir, it's just a question whether this serves as an אוהל.
ohel. An umbrella. So the גמרא Gemara. says, so the גמרא Gemara
says ומר סבר לא שמיה אוהל. u-mar savar lo shemei ohel. והתניא...
Ve-ha tanya... Now there's a whole question whether you read והתניא ve-ha
tanya here as a question or as a support.
I'm going to read it as a support. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosef
be-Rabbi Yehuda says: תיבה שמלאה
כלים וזרקה בפני המת, tevah she-melei'ah kelim ve-zarkah bifnei ha-met, if you
have a box filled with
כלים kelim, and you threw it and it flew over the dead
body, okay, בפני המת, bifnei ha-met, באוהל טמאה. be-ohel tmei'ah. ואם הייתה
מונחת טהורה. Ve-im haytah munachat, tehorah. So if it
is—so if it basically is like is an אוהל ohel over the
מת, then it is טמאה tmei'ah because that box does not serve
as an אוהל. ohel. The phrase באוהל be-ohel is a little funny,
it sounds like there's an אוהל ohel over the box and over
the dead body, but most likely it means that to be able,
you know, if you're in a house, then that טומאה tumah should
transfer like through the roof of the, you know, through the ceiling
of the house to the dead body. But anyway, it means that
it's—you threw it and it creates an אוהל ohel over the מת.
So it's טמאה, tmei'ah, but if it was מונחת, munachat, if it
was if it was actually the box were just suspended on like
poles over the dead body, then טהורה tehorah it would be טהור.
tahor. So that shows you the idea of an אוהל זרוק ohel
zaruk is not שמיה אוהל. shemei ohel. Now, the problem with that
is, is that fine, that shows you—right, you got it? Like in
a flying box, the כלים kelim in it are טמא tamei? because
the box is... doesn't... you get the scenario, yeah? I'm talking about
an airplane. No, I'm not talking about an airplane. I have, I
have this, this is my box. This is filled with כלים. This
is my dead body. It's got a cover over this, I'm not
going to spill it. Okay, I throw it over the מת. Okay,
now there's a טפח tefach between the מת and the bottom of
the box, it's got a טפח tefach by טפח, tefach, it's an
אוהל ohel should protect the כלים. But it says no, it says
the כלים in it are טמא, tamei the טומאה tumah goes through.
This is not—does not constitute an אוהל. ohel. If, however, it were
suspended on sticks above the dead body, then it would be an
אוהל ohel and the כלים would be okay. But if it's flying
over the dead body, it's an אוהל זרוק, ohel zaruk, it's a
moving אוהל, ohel, then this—does this—it does not constitute an אוהל ohel
and the טומאה tumah goes into it. So then it's like the
airplane. Right, that's what I meant. Fine. So now that seems to
be the principle that אוהל זרוק לא שמיה אוהל. ohel zaruk lo
shemei ohel. The problem with that is, is that רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda, if you look two lines from the
top, remind yourself what his position was, it said רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה מטהר. Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda metaher. He said the guy going
through ארץ העמים Eretz Ha'ammim in the box is טהור. tahor. And
here רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda says the box
filled with the כלים, the כלים are טמא. tamei, Okay, so because...
you see the problem?
Yes? He says the box filled with כלים, the box is not
an אוהל, ohel, they're טמא, tamei but he said the guy being
transported in the box, the guy is טהור. tahor. So תוספות Tosafot
reads this, one version is reading this as a question. You can't
say רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosef be-Rabbi Yehuda says an אוהל
זרוק ohel zaruk is שמיה אוהל. shemei ohel. Look, he says the
כלים in the box are טמא. tamei, Okay, the other way of
reading it is that actually it's not a question, that there's different
degrees of זרוק. zaruk. זורק. zorak. Okay, there's the זורק zorak of
you're throwing it and it's just going by its own momentum, nothing
is, you know, keeping it up other than it's
like gravity is pulling it down, it's just going to fall eventually.
He says that's like a classical זורק. zorak. Like another example would
be if you've got a טלית talis that's flapping in the wind,
you know, the wind picked it up and it's flapping around, that's
a classical זורק. zorak. He says that's different than being transported by
the box. Why? Because if people are transporting you in the box,
they're standing on the ground, right? So the fact that they happen
to be moving, is that an אהל זורק? ohel zorak? I mean,
they're moving but you're also anchored on the ground by their bodies,
right?
So תוספות Tosafot says that maybe is a questionable אהל זורק. ohel
zorak. So the way תוספות Tosafot wants to read this גרסא girsa
now not as a question but as a proof is look, everybody
agrees to the principle that a real אהל זורק ohel zorak if
it has no support, it's just being thrown, okay, then that is
לא שמיה אהל. lo shemeh ohel. Okay, everybody agrees with that. The
debate of רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yosi bar Yehuda and of
רבי Rebbi is whether that would apply even to a box that's
being transported and that the people that are and that there are
people on the ground who are holding it up, or an elephant
on the ground or something on the ground that's holding it up,
okay, right, the guy on the top of the elephant. All right,
so that's basically, we're going to read it that way. So you
have this guy's being transported in ארץ העמים Eretz Amim in this
box,
and it's a debate whether he's טהור tahor or טמא. tamei, One
way of understanding that is is it the issue about the אויר,
avir, and רש"י Rashi says no, here's another way of understanding it.
Everybody agrees that a real אהל זורק ohel zorak is not an
אהל, ohel, okay? And here, the question is it's not a real
אהל זורק ohel zorak because there are people that are on the
one hand it's moving, it's not fully stationary, and on the other
hand, there are people that are anchoring it on the ground and
they could stop at any time. So that's what the debate is,
whether that constitutes an אהל זורק ohel zorak or not. Everybody agrees
it's גוש. gush. Everybody agrees a real אהל זורק ohel zorak is
not שמיה אהל, shemeh ohel, and here the debate is does this
scenario constitute an אהל זורק ohel zorak or not? Yes.
Conceptually the issue being anchored on the ground or is the issue
that it can hover even if it's in the air, because then
seriously there'd be a difference between that and an airplane?
Right, or let's think, right, or right, or let's take another example.
Let's say you had something that was going downhill on wheels. You
had something in a wagon that was going downhill on wheels, right,
it could not nobody was able to control it to stop, but
it was anchored on the ground. Right, so you could so both
of those are relevant factors. Yes, exactly.
But the classic one has neither of those. It's a flapping טלית,
talis, it's a thrown box, right, there's nothing that anchors it and
there's nothing that keeps it up. Okay, yes.
In ancient times, didn't they transport these children on an animal with
wood above them to protect them as an אהל? ohel?
Yes, that's a good point, that that's true. So that would have
to I think תוספות Tosafot, there actually discusses the אהל זורק, ohel
zorak, that's an excellent point because that's right, because they would transport
the kids and they would protect them because they would have that
plank, but they would it would be in transportation. So that would
have to assume that this wouldn't be an אהל זורק ohel zorak
because it is anchored. So you're you're right, that's an excellent point.
And what you would do if you would say that would be
an אהל זורק, ohel zorak, I don't know, but yes, it's a
very good point. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara so that's one
way of explaining the debate, not based on אויר, avir, but whether
this constitutes אהל זורק. ohel zorak.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara, says like this. אלא ela
now if we have that as a proof, not as a question,
then the גרסא girsa isn't אלא but איבעית אימא. I ba'it eima.
Okay, so we're going to read it that way, I think it's
a smoother way of reading the גמרא. Gemara. איבעית אימא I ba'it
eima if you want, here's another way of explaining the debate, not
about אויר avir and גוש. gush. So one way of explaining it
is that it's about גוש gush but it's because of what are
the parameters of אהל זורק. ohel zorak. Here's another way of explaining
the debate. איבעית אימא, I ba'it eima, it says דכולי עלמא משום
אויר. de-chulei alma mishum avir.
It is about the air. So it's about the air,
and on the one hand so it's about the air, so if
it's about the air, why isn't everybody saying you're טמא? tamei You're
in the box, it's open, you're exposed to the air. ומר סבר
כיון דלא שכיח לא גזרו ביה רבנן ומר סבר אף על גב
דלא שכיח גזרו ביה רבנן. u-mar savar keivan de-lo shechiach lo gazru
bei rabanan u-mar savar af al gav de-lo shechiach gazru bei rabanan.
So this is very strange, right? Okay, yes, it's about the air,
but it's very rare to be exposed to the air because you're
in this box, okay, that you're being transported in a box and
that's the only way you're exposed to the air. So maybe even
though technically you are exposed to the air, we're not going to
say you're טמא tamei. because it's a very uncommon thing. Now, that
raises two questions. First of all, what is a common scenario of
being exposed to the air and not being over the ground, right?
If you're saying that the air is טמא, tamei? then the reason
you're saying that is to cover cases where you're not טמא tamei
because of your you're over the ground. So if this isn't a
common scenario of that context of being exposed to the air, what
is a common scenario? That's question number one. But question number two
is, it's just completely bizarre to say, okay, we're going to call
the air טמא, tamei. but you can come in contact with the
air and be טהור tahor as the way you come in contact
with it is in an unusual way. It's like, you know, once
you are giving a... status to the air of ארץ העמים, eretz
ha'amim, right, when we say דבר לא שכיח לא גזרו ביה רבנן,
davar lo shchiach lo gazru beih rabbanan, that might be if I'm
going to say, you know, you shouldn't engage in certain types of,
I don't know, practices like on, I don't know, like on חול
המועד, chol hamoed, you know, you can't do, you know, laundry or
this or that or whatever, but maybe in a particular case it
was לא שכיח, lo shchiach, we didn't say it was prohibited in
that case. That's when what I'm focusing on is don't engage in
this practice, and I mean it for like the vast normal range
of cases. If you have a very unusual scenario, I never meant
to prohibit that type of a case. That's when what we're doing
is prohibiting actions, right. You could say it didn't prohibit these rare
cases. But if what we're doing is assigning a status and we're
saying the air space is טמא, tamei so what is it? Oh,
but the air space stops being טמא tamei when the way you
came in contact with it was an unusual way. I think it's
very bizarre to apply the idea of דבר לא שכיח לא גזרו
רבנן davar lo shchiach lo gazru rabbanan when we're not dealing with
prohibiting actions but with creating a status of an object. Okay, so
really fun, now but let's get back, so that's a real big
question, but let's get back to the other question of if this
is לא שכיח, lo shchiach, what is שכיח? shchiach? So if you
take a look at תוספות, Tosafot תוספות Tosafot. says the following.
He says,
he
probably says this.
Yeah, he has
איבעית אימא. iba'it eima. איבעית אימא, iba'it eima, yes, that's what I
said, yes. So he says like this, okay. Oh well, let's read
the next line in the גמרא Gemara and then we'll get back
to תוספות. Tosafot ומר סבר לא שכיח לא גזרו ביה רבנן ומר
סבר אף על גב דלא שכיח גזרו ביה רבנן, umar savar lo
shchiach lo gazru beih rabbanan umar savar af al gav delo shchiach
gazru beih rabbanan, because—actually it's in the גמרא—הנכנס לארץ העמים בשידה תיבה
ומגדל טהור. tahor. ובקרון ובספינה—I uvakaron uvisfinah have to go to תוספות—גמרא,
ובקרון ובספינה ובאיסקריא טמא. uvakaron uvisfinah uveis'karya tamei.
If you go in and you're being transported in a box, you're
טהור. tahor. If however you go in and you're in a wagon
or in a boat or an איסקריא, is'karya, which I think is
like the mast of a boat, okay, then you're, and you're in
the air space but you're not on the ground, then you're טמא.
tamei So the question is what's the difference? Right, what's the difference
if you're in a wagon or if you're in a box? Either
way, right, you're in, you're in the air space of ארץ העמים
eretz ha'amim without being over the ground because you're being protected by
an אוהל. ohel. So the only difference is one is a normal
way of going into ארץ העמים. eretz ha'amim. How do you get
into ארץ העמים? eretz ha'amim? You go in by a wagon, you
go in by a boat. The other is a non-normal way, having
people carry you in a box. Okay, so the only logic of
these differences, there's no difference between are you exposed to the air,
there's no difference of whether it constitutes an אוהל. ohel. The only
difference between the box and the wagon is, is it normal or
not normal? So this shows that it's משום אווירא mishum avira and
even though it's משום אווירא, mishum avira, they only applied it to
normal cases, not to non-normal cases. Yes.
I mean, I don't understand, a box, if you're in a box,
you have, you're in the...
No, we're assuming the top is open. Oh, so you'd have to
have air, you'd have to breathe, but that's what we're assuming for
the purpose of argument, I mean for the purpose of explaining this.
Oh, that could be why you're טהור. tahor. Oh, that could be,
right, maybe, yeah, that's an interesting point. But then why would it
distinguish between the box and between a wagon? You could also be
in like a covered wagon, you know.
The wagon's, I mean, inevitably open at,
right, like to get in and out. Well, you also have to
get in and out of a box. I mean, I mean, well,
maybe. Okay. Anyway, that's the way, maybe, maybe you could have said
that, but that's the way the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so we now
have two ways of explaining the debate. One is everybody says that
it's משום גוש, mishum gush, and the question about being in the
box is, is that, does that constitute an אוהל זרוק ohel zaruk
to be, to separate between the טומאה tumah of the ground? The
second way is everybody agrees it's אווירא, avira, and the only, and
yes, you are exposed to the אווירא, avira, but the question is,
maybe with אווירא avira because that's a bizarre idea that air is
מטמא, we'll only apply it to normal ways of entering the air
space, not to non-normal ways of entering the air space, and the
box is a non-normal way. One minute, and let's have a third
possibility. ואיבעית אימא ve'iba'it eima if you want, הכא שמא יוציא ראשו
ורובו לשם פליגי. hacha shema yotzi rosho verubo lesham pligi. That basically
it's about the גוש, gush, let's say, and if you're, yes, you're
in the air space but you're not out, well, hold on, let
me just make sure.
One minute. Yes, it's because of the גוש. gush. We're going to
assume that the box is an אוהל. ohel. So here you are,
you're in the box, okay, and you're being carried over, here people
are carrying you, okay,
okay, people are carrying you, you're in the box, this is the
ground. So yes, you're in the air space, but we're saying it's
not the air space, it's the גוש. gush. You're protected because we're
going to assume that is an אוהל. ohel. That's not an אוהל
זרוק, ohel zaruk, that is an אוהל. ohel. So why would you
be טמא? tamei So if, if it's about the גוש, gush, right
now you are טהור. tahor But maybe we'll say you're טמא tamei
because we're afraid you're going to lean over. And if you'll lean
over, that's when the טומאה will come and get you from the
ground.
Even in the box?
No, but only because of אוהל, ohel, only because of אוהל, ohel,
not that the air itself is טמא. tamei, It's only normal rules
of אוהל. ohel. If it was just air, you'd be טמא tamei,
here because you're exposed to the אוויר. avir. But it's not. It's
the ground of ארץ העמים. eretz ha'amim. But the concern is so
maybe you'll lean over and that's why we would make you טמא
tamei. even before you leaned over. Okay. ואיבעית אימא, ve'ibayas eima, so
if you want, הכא שמא יוציא ראשו ורובו לשם פליגי, hacha shema
yotzi rosho verubo lesham pligi, ודתניא, vedatanya, we taught a ברייתא, braita,
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda omer, הנכנס לארץ
העמים בשידה תיבה ומגדל טהור hanichnas le'eretz ha'amim beshidah tevah umigdal tahor.
עד שיוציא לשם ראשו או רובו, ad sheyotzi lesham rosho o rubo,
that
he says if you go in you're טהור until you actually, you
know, lean over your body and the most of your body, then
you would actually be טמא tamei which shows, which seems to be
because he says עד שיוציא ad sheyotzi reflects the idea that that's
the concern. There's a concern that you might do that and the
חכמים hachamim who say you're טמא tamei immediately, presumably they're saying you're
טמא because we're afraid you've already done that. And he is saying,
no no no, you're not טמא, if you do it you'll be
טמא, but until you do it you're not טמא. Now the funny
thing is, if it's really משום גושא, mishum gusha, why does it
have to be ראשו ורובו? rosho verubo? Like even a piece, remember
the גמרא Gemara with your nose in the house? Hard to forget
that גמרא. So maybe even a little bit of your body. So
even this is not so clear, but basically we have a range
of possibilities. It could be a debate of airspace versus ground in
terms of the issue of the box, that's what the גמרא first
says and that's the easiest thing to say: the ground is protected,
the airspace you're exposed. Or a whole range of other possibilities. Everybody
agrees that it's airspace, but airspace is a bizarre thing, so it's
only when you go in in a normal way, this might not
be considered a normal way. Everybody agrees it's ground, but the question
is whether this constitutes an אהל זרוק ohel zaruk to protect you,
or everybody agrees that it's ground, but you know, are we going
to say you're טמא anyway because it's so likely that you're going
to put your body out of the box that will make you
טמא already right now? All right, so right range of positions in
terms of that. We'll end with this now.
When you say, when you say the אהל ohel is protecting you
in that scenario the diagram, the אהל ohel is upside down, right?
In a way?
Well, but the floor, no, this is the... but effectively the אהל
ohel is the roof, right?
Yeah,
but like if you're in a two-story building,
right, right, and you're in the second story and the מת is
down here, it's the same point. What's for you is the floor
is what for the מת is the roof.
There's no sides to that, but in your diagram there's no sides.
Doesn't have to be sides, an אהל ohel is just a top.
Just a top. Oh gotcha.
If it's אוירא avira you don't even need an אהל. ohel.
If it's אוירא avira right,
I mean if it's אוירא avira then even if you're protected you're
exposed to the air.
Everything is...
you need a space suit.
Don't mean out the box, everywhere.